Guide to the Gay Cable Network Archives, 1982-2001 MSS.231
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series XI: Gay USA
  - 1991 Vol. IX
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 7 [Air date: 2/14/1991], February 1991; ID: 231.0285 (Box 18, Media ID: 231.0285)
      4. GLADD event. Craig Davidson, founding executive director, talks about stepping down from GLAAD to focus on GLAAD USA, which would make GLAAD a national organization with unified chapters. Davidson is presented with a piece of a steel girder by co-chair Dennis Lonigan at the ceremony. Davidson talks about GLAAD's founding principles. Karen Schwartz, director of public affairs and programming for GLAAD talks about Davidson. Lonigan introduces Stephen Beck, the new executive director for GLAAD, and gives him a steel girder as well. Beck is interviewed about expanding GLAAD's goals.
      5. All About Women: Rebecca Lewin speaks to Sheryl Miller, a delegate to the Middle East Children's Alliance. Footage shot by Miller in Iraq is shown. Miller talks peace activism in Iraq, discusses that most of her conversations were probably taped while in Iraq, and the baby boom in Iraq.
      6. GCN Special Report. Matt Forman from the Anti-Violence Project is interviewed about a 'near riot' in Midtown north that stemmed from a protest against police brutality. Forman talks about how the police went for people with press credentials first 'to get rid of videotape evidence of what was going on'. Footage of the protest is then shown (Footage and Commentary: David Meieran, Out in the 90s). Forman talks about trying to reform the way police respond to these protests and launch an investigation. Forman talks about how 10% of the 900 reports the Anti-Violence Project received in 1990 stemmed from police abuse. A call is made for anyone who was at the demonstration to call the Anti-Violence Project.
      7. Martin Duberman, who is giving talks at the Museum of Natural History on gay and lesbian past (as part of the Margaret Mead series) is interviewed. Talks about how the New York Historical Society was the only other time he was able to lecture to a crowd about gay history (part of the program Whose History?).
      BUMPER: Happy Valentine's Gay
      8. Lavender Health: Frank Oldham, acting director for the Office of Lesbian and Gay Health Concerns, interviews Dennis deLeon of the NYC Human Rights Commission about a domestic registration project as part of the first step to a domestic partnership law, anti-gay-and-lesbian violence (deLeon: 'it has gone higher than any other group'), eliminating hiring practices that discriminate against gays and lesbians, the need for a hate crime bill, and how AIDS has become part of the stigma against homosexuals. Education is emphasized to help quell stereotypes. Emphasis is placed on getting the word out to Albany, and getting statewide support.
      9. Naming Names: Joe Windish of GLAAD talks about the lesbian kiss episode of "L.A. Law", which marked the first recurring bisexual character on a primetime show, and has made strides in portraying gay and lesbian characters. Encourages writing letters of support to David E Kelley, the executive producer of the show.
      10. Andy Humm outro.
      Credits over a music video for "Give Peace a Chance"
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 8 [Air date: 2/21/1991], February 1991; ID: 231.0286 (Box 18, Media ID: 231.0286)
      1. Andy Humm talks about how most of the previous night's show was not broadcast because the tape was jammed, which means most of this episode is actually a repeat of the last one.
      2. Top story on how someone spray-painted 'O'CONNOR SPREADS DEATH' on Cardinal O'Connor's Madison Avenue residence. Three people nearby were arrested, 'roughed up', and verbally abused by police. David Meirian's footage from segment 6 of 0285 is repeated. Humm interviews Lori Cohen, an attorney (also part of ACT UP) on the rash of police brutality. Scott Sensenig is mentioned, with a cutaway to his photo in the Village Voice where he has 'two black eyes and a five-inch gash across his forehead'. Graffiti artist Michael Griffith is mentioned. The two discuss the North Precinct incident; Cohen states that the deputy commissioner got paint on his new shoes, and in retaliation sent his police to attack the crowd. One of the only arrests was someone who was videotaping the event. Chris Henley, who suffered a debilitating concussion during the scuffle, is planning to sue the police. Cohen discusses how there has been no response from any level of government or police on the issue. Humm mentions a March 3rd demonstration in Times Square. There is talk about how Manhattan North has always had a bad reputation with gays and lesbians. Humm is then joined by Matt Foreman from the Anti-Violence Project. Foreman talks about how three escort services have recently robbed people. Foreman advises people use word of mouth, and only go with services that use credit cards instead of cash-only. Foreman then discusses that there is an anti-activist feeling among police and an increased militarism because of the recent Gulf War. Cohen talks about how most of the charges against the demonstrators will most likely be dropped because there's little evidence. Foreman talks about being 'weary' of going to demonstrations because he believes he will at some point be targeted by police.
      3. Andy Humm talks about domestic partnerships in San Francisco, and that rights groups are trying to get the same thing done in New York.
      4. Laura Sabia interviews Andrea Burnstein, deputy press secretary to Liz Holtzman. Burnstein talks about moving to New York in 1985 and being involved with gay and lesbian activism. Burnstein talks about the bias bill, and domestic partnership bill. Talks about coming out at work.
      COMMERCIAL: Night of a Thousand Gowns.
      5. GCN goes to Montreal. Montage set to French-language version of "New York, New York".
      6. Same as 0285, segment 5
      7. Lavender Health: Harold Robinson, assistant project coordinator for Men of Color AIDS Prevention Project, interviews commissioner Dennis deLeon. (While the introductions are done, the phone in De Leon's office rings). deLeon talks about his roots in the Latino community, and how his office is the only one in the country where you can bring a lawsuit against someone for sexual orientation discrimination. deLeon says his main two goals are addressing employment discrimination, inter-group relations, and AIDS advocacy. Phone number is displayed for deLeon's office.
      8. Apart from a new intro with Andy Humm, the same as 0285 segment 7.
      9. Naming Names: Scott Sherman of GLAAD talks about "The Silence of the Lambs" perpetuating gay bias. The address of Eric Pleskow, president of Orion Pictures ("Lambs"' distributor) is displayed. Director Jonathan Demme is also named.
      10. Shortened repeat of 0285 segment 4.
      11. GCN Special Report: On location with the protest against police brutality. Matt Forman is interviewed, and there are many gay organizations in attendance. Forman talks about the enormous police presence at this protest.
      12. Andy Humm talks about upcoming memorial service for Jonathan Logan.
      Credits roll over B-roll of the rally.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 9 [Air date: 2/28/1991], February 1991; ID: 231.0287A (Box 18, Media ID: 231.0287A)
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 10 [Air date: 3/7/1991] [Empty], March 1991; ID: 231.0288 (Box 18, Media ID: 231.0288)
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 11 [Air date: 3/14/1991] [Empty], March 1991; ID: 231.0289 (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0289)
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 12 [Air date: 3/21/1991], March 1991; ID: 231.0290 (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0290)
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 13 [Air date: 3/28/1991], March 1991; ID: 231.0291A (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0291A)
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 14 [Air date: 4/4/1991], April 1991; ID: 231.0292 (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0292)
      1. ROTC removed from the John Jay College campus because of their discrimination against gays and lesbians. Pedro Velazquez, president of the Lambda Club at JJC is interviewed. Marjorie Hill is mentioned. Velazquez faced little opposition to his surprise. Dick Cheney and his lesbian daughter are mentioned.
      2. Protest at Gov. Mario Cuomo's NYC office on April 2, 1991. Cuomo was cutting AIDS funding. ACT UP is protesting with 'die-ins' where every eight minutes, the protesters lay on the ground.
      3. ACT UP protests the Academy Awards on March 25, 1991 for not addressing AIDS. This protest garnered national media coverage and was done right outside the venue that hosted the Oscars.
      COMMERCIALl: Hair Club For Men
      4. All About Women: Rebecca Lewin interviews Kitty Cotter of the Bronx Lesbians United in Sisterhood about domestic partnership benefits. Elizabeth Holtzman and Fernando Ferer supported the bill. Domestic partnership benefits for city employees only; need approval from Albany for statewide coverage.
      5. Rich Flowers interviews John Gilgun, author of Music I Never Dreamed Of, about a young man from Boston in the 1950s.
      6. Lavender Health: Frank Oldham interviews Elliot Rivera, the HIV Communication Program Planner, Department of Health. Rivera has spearheaded anti-discrimination and making people comfortable around gays.
      7. Interview with John Canalli, director of the Alphabit Land video, which covers Wigstock '90. A clip is shown of Michael West performing as Liza Minelli singing "Let It Be".
      8. Naming Names: Kirk-Evan Billet of GLAAD discusses an Oklahoma City radio personality, Mark Shannon, who made extremely homophobic remarks during his radio shows. Viewers are instructed to write to the station manager at KRXO, and advises them to send a copy of the letter to the FCC.
      COMMERCIAL: Hair Club For Men
      9. Priscilla Ehly interviews members of SAGE, Ruby Juster and Diane Chambers about an upcoming event with Deborah Glick, and Women's Dance at The Limelight.
      10. Lou Maletta interviews Suzanne Westenhoefer, the first openly gay comedian ever featured on television, who had recently appeared on Sally Jesse Raphael.
      11. Andy Humm announces Gay USA will broadcast in San Francisco.
      Credits roll over footage of Suzanne Westenhoefer's stand-up.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 15 [Air date: 4/11/1991], April 1991; ID: 231.0293 (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0293)
      1. Andy Humm talks about a supposed lesbian affair Nancy Reagan had, an allegation that Ronald Reagan date-raped a young girl before marriage, and a "20/20" segment about the exclusion of gays in the military. After the segment, Barbara Walters made a comment about how there were compelling arguments on both sides, to which her guest, Katherine Hepburn chastised her.
      2. Rich Flowers interviews openly-gay umpire Dave Pallone's autobiography "Behind the Mask: My Double Life in Baseball". Mention is made of the Saratoga sex scandal.
      3. ACT-UP's Needle Exchange Demonstration outside the NYC Criminal Court on April 8, 1991. This was in response to a needle exchange program that landed several members of ACT-UP on trial because they were giving clean needles to drug addicts. Gay Wachman of the Needle Exchange Committee reads a mission statement. Valmeanette Montgomery, State Senator (D) and Joseph L. Galiber, another State Senator (D) speaks to reporters about decriminalizing the distribution of sterile needles. Deborah Glick of the State Assembly and Dr. Mathilda Krim, the co-founder of AMFAR also voice their support.
      4. WeeWah and Bar Chee Ampe, Lesbian and Gay Native Americans of NYC. Curtis Harris and Leota Longdog, founding members of the group are interviewed about a coming out party occurring in NYC. An excerpt of one of the group's dances is shown.
      COMMERCIAl: Hair Club For Men
      5. Police Commissioner Lee Brown speaks at Columbia University's youth conference. Protesters from Queer Nation are there to voice disapproval, which stems from the rash of police brutality. Activist Bob Raffsky interrupts Brown's speech and gets applause.
      6. Samantha Palazola of the Pink Panthers is interviewed about getting new members and support. Sue Hennesey has an audio-only interview over footage of a nightclub.
      7. Lavender Health: Gregory Broyles of the Black Leadership Commission on AIDS is interviewed about the ties the organization has to the Urban League and the early days of his organization, and how he assists in his community.
      8. Emily Woo Yamasaki, a member of Radical Women, is interviewed about her organization. Their address and phone number are displayed.
      Commercial: Hair Club For Men
      9. Naming Names: Karin Schwartz of GLAAD talks about LIFE magazine's interview with Faye Yaeger, and her uncommented-upon homophobic comments. The address for Jim Gaines, the managing editor of Life Magazine is displayed.
      10. GCN Sports: Gay and Lesbian Singles Tennis Tournament, Wrestlemania is recommended, GWAC is mentioned. Footage from the Gotham Volleyball League is shown. There is a video hiccup where part of Rich Flowers' commentary suddenly starts then stops in the middle of the footage. Unity 94 is made to change their logo by the Olympic Committee due to the logo having interlocking rings.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 16 [Air date: [4]/18/1991], April 1991; ID: 231.0294 (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0294)
      1. Lambda Independent Democrats hosts former vice-presidential candidate Geraldine Ferraro. Ferraro, who was then running for senate at the time, speaks on issues close to the gay community. Andy Humm interviews Ferraro after her speech, as well as a woman whose name is not displayed (referred to as 'Ms. Garrow'), the president of the Lambda club (he is not named), and the executive director of the Empire State Pride Agenda (again, not named) about their reactions to Ferraro's speech.
      2. Lou Maletta interviews participants in a mock gay wedding outside of a post office on tax day.
      3. ACT UP! Fights Back at City Hall for Homeless People With AIDS. No group trying to create housing for AIDS victims is unable to do so because of contracts.
      COMMERCIAL: AIDS Walk New York
      4. All About Women: Prinny Alavi, fine arts photographer is interviewed. Some of Prinny Alavi's photos are shown throughout. [During this segment, behind-the-scenes chatter can very clearly be heard throughout the entire nine-minute segment.]
      5. Thomas H. Sauerman, executive director of PFLAG (and Lutheran minister) is interviewed about his organization. Sauerman talks about his young son coming out of the closet, and how this made him come to accept homosexuals. [From 26:54 to 26:58, the screen goes blank. Also, a cameraman is having a coughing fit during the latter half of the interview.]
      6. Deep Dish with D. Isidore: Louis Katz, former owner of the Uncle Charlie's bar is covered. Isidore accuses Katz of killing multiple men he was stalking, and says that authorities should be on the lookout for Katz, who was then a fugitive.
      7. Andy Humm encourages viewers to send pictures of Lou Katz.
      8. Julian Clary of Sticky Moments is interviewed about his childhood and college years, his cabaret act, and how Sticky Moments came to be. A few clips from Sticky Moments are shown.
      9. Lavender Health: Frank Oldham interviews Elliot Rivera from the Department of Health about dealing with homophobia in AIDS education.
      10. Naming Names: Dr. Henry Yeager of GLAAD about the use of the term 'pansy' in a Bloomingdales ad. Viewers are encouraged to write to John Jay, the director of advertising at Bloomingdales.
      11. Gay and lesbian southerners celebrate in New York with weekly dinners. Several southerners are interviewed about their childhoods and adolescence in the Bible belt.
      12. Lee Sharmat is named the new co-host of Gay USA.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 17 [Air date: 4/25/1991], April 1991; ID: 231.0295 (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0295)
      1. Connecticut becomes fourth state to pass laws that protect gay and lesbian rights. Dick Dadey, the executive director of the Pride Agenda discusses the difficulties in getting a similar bill passed in New York due to the Republican-controlled senate. Mention is made of Lobby Day (May 3-7) in Albany, in which they march on the state capitol.
      2. May 1st is a benefit for Chris Hennely, who was beaten by police in the North Precinct riot. Viewers are encouraged to watch WNET (mention is made that the boycott doesn't stand at this point) for an hour-long program on gay youth hosted by GCN's own Andy Humm. The re-release of "Spartacus" is mentioned, which restored a dialogue scene that had homosexual and bisexual subtext. A town called Gay Head in Martha's Vineyard is trying to change its name.
      3. The 2nd Annual GLAAD Media Awards at the World Trade Center. Karin Schwartz is interviewed. Phil Donahue gives out the awards. Beth Nissen, an ABC News correspondent accepts an award on behalf of ABC News. Craig Davison, Peggy Shaw, and Lois Weaver also appear. Anti-awards are given to Pat Buchanan and Donald Wildman (American Family Association).
      4. Part two of the GLAAD awards. Victor Zonana of the LA Times speaks at the podium. Kim McGuire introduces Jane Gross of The New York Times. Meredith Baxter-Birney introduces James Hart, producer of "L.A. Law". John Lithgow introduces "Longtime Companion" star Bruce Davidson.
      COMMERCIAL: Laser Medical Associates (public domain clips)
      5. Robert Parker previews the New Museum's upcoming auction, interviewing curator Gary Sangster.
      COMMERCIAL: Pump, Opening Night at The Bank.
      COMMERCIAL: Stride With Pride
      6. Medical Update with Jeffery Lavigne: Lavigne heads up Laser Medical Associates, which specializes in anal surgeries. Lavigne talks about being 'a gay man in a straight world'.
      7. Lavender Health: Harold Robinson interviews Gregory Broyles of the Lifestyle Genesis Program, a workshop series about the service gap for black gay men. People of Color In Crisis is mentioned. Broyles talks about how the association came about.
      8. GCN Sports: BASL begins to allow women in their league. WANY, Brooklyn Women's Martial Arts School, Gotham Sports Association, and IGBO are mentioned. A good portion of the segment is devoted to talking about how people do not like to be filmed at these sporting events (a large subtitle reading 'Commentary' appears at the bottom third of the screen during this segment).
      9. Naming Names: Cheryl Moch of GLAAD, addresses how the magazine Essence refused to publish an ad for The Black Gay and Lesbian Conference, but backed down once LAMBDA threatened to sue them. The then-current issue of Essence detailed the senior editor's coming out. Contact info for Edward Lewis, publisher of Essence, is displayed.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 18 [Air date: 5/[2]/1991], May 1991; ID: 231.0296 (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0296)
      1. A fan letter from Russia is read. Mario Cuomo proposes a gay rights bill after Connecticut passes a similar bill. Andy Humm mentions the march on Albany is 'next week'. A New York Post story about Mary McFaddin's divorce is discussed. Andy Humm announces that there will be hearings on police brutality, mentions Chris Hennelly. Get well wishes are sent out to Damien Martin, who was mugged.
      2. Coverage of the National Lesbian Conference in Atlanta. Jo Garner, head of the Lesbian-Gay Task Force, Michelle Crone, Mandy Carter, Barb Bechdol, and Stephanie Jo Kent, conference organizers, Robin Tyler, an activist, and Urvashi Vaid speak at the podium. 'Zaum', Pat Carroll, and is interviewed.
      COMMERCIAL: NAYA Natural Spring Water
      3. Out! Auction, an organization which fights censorship of art, and is the largest gay and lesbian art association, is covered. Tory Osborne, executive director of the Gay and Lesbian Community Center interviews Sean Strub.
      4. Andy Humm interviews Andrew Morgan from the AIDS Council of New South Wales about AIDS treatment in Australia, focusing on education outreach and needle exchanges. Australia's extremely stringent drug approval laws are covered. A commercial from the Victorian AIDS Council is shown. Morgan strongly recommends needle exchange programs.
      5. Lou Maletta interviews Jane DeLynn, a lesbian war correspondent. She discusses the difficulty in getting a Visa, the Coast Guard's support of her travelling, and her time in Saudi Arabia. DeLynn's personal photos are shown.
      6. Between the Covers: Rich Flowers interviews Paul Monette, an author who has written several books about AIDS, including "Borrowed Time". Monette is asked if he is afraid of dying because he is HIV-positive. He replies that he's afraid of being sick more than dying.
      COMMERCIAL: Third-Annual Lambda Literary Awards
      7. Lavender Health: Sean Dwyer interviews Michael Picucci about treating alcoholism among gays and lesbians. Gambling, smoking, and sex addiction are also covered.
      8. Scott Sherman from GLAAD praises Golf Illustrated for an article about lesbian golf players. Viewers are instructed to write praise to Golf Illustrated.
      9. Viewers are encouraged to attend the March in Albany.
    - Gay USA, Vol. IX, Episode No. 19 [Air date: 5/7/1991], May 1991; ID: 231.0297A (Box 19, Media ID: 231.0297A)
      1. Andy Humm reports that the New York High Court ruled that a lesbian partner who participated in the planning and birth of a child, is not entitled to visitation rights in the event of a break-up or divorce. Coverage is given to a New Jersey judge who ruled surgeons with AIDS must inform their patients. Senator Charles Robb's embarrassing sex scandal is covered. The Committee of the Presbyterian Church issues liberal views on sexuality and marriage. Cardinal John O'Connor still trying to ban condoms in high schools.
      2. Robert Parker and Lou Maletta report from Albany on Stride With Pride. This was organized to get support for the bias bill. Libby Post, Matt Foreman, and Dick Dadey are interviewed. Speeches by Tim Mains of the Rochester City Council, Deborah Glick of the New York State assembly are shown. An effigy is burned of Ralph Marino. Three teens talk about being attacked and chased by a homophobic crowd outside McDonalds during the event.
      3. Queer Nation Atlanta Protests Cracker Barrel. Footage is shown from one of several protests that occurred because of Cracker Barrel's policy of firing gay employees. The protesters occupied the building and staged a sit-in.
      4. ACT UP! Marches on Albany for prisoners with AIDS. The ACLU joins the protest as well, which is about the lack of treatment and healthcare for prisoners with AIDS.
      5. Ads Against AIDS. Neil Calet and Robert Starr are interviewed.
      6. Second part of the interview with Jane DeLynn. Homes and cities in Saudi Arabia are shown. DeLynn comments the war was 'put on for TV'.
      COMMERCIAL: Outweek
      7. A lengthy excerpt from the play 'Angel and Dragon' is shown. Lou Maletta interviews Sally Netzel, the playwright.
      8. Lavender Health: Ellen Zaltsberg interviews Sandy Lowe, an attorney at Lambda legal defense about the controversy over "Miss Saigon" and the nature of sexism and racism.
      COMMERCIAL: GCN's 9th Anniversary at The Bank
      9. GCN Sports: Opening ceremonies for the Big Apple Softball League and opening game for the Women Athletes of New York. Mention is made that New York Magazine did a story on adult sports programs in NY, which made no mention of gay sports groups.
      10. Naming Names: GLAAD San Francisco protests "Basic Instinct's" production. Carolco got a restraining order against GLAAD. Viewers are encouraged to write to Peter Hoffman of Carolco.
      11. Lou Maletta announces the passing of Phil Zwickler.